Tens of millions of people use it every
day as a pill form of an health
insurance policy. You might use it, too.
It's the all-encompassing multivitamin.
And I was curious to find out if
multivitamins are really all that
beneficial, especially against one of
the leading causes of death, cancer. So,
as usual, I pulled eight studies on the
topic, and what I discovered was
affirming in many ways and slightly
worrisome in others. If you look at the
studies that look at multivitamin use
and cancer occurrence, meaning that are
you more or less likely to get cancer,
there's generally good news on that
front with one rather large oddity
between men and women that I'll touch on
in a bit. The interesting part though is
when getting into the disagreeing
studies like these that indicate no
effect of multivitamin use like we see
here. The higher the lines go, the more
invasive cancer has occurred since the
lines don't deviate from one another in
an obvious way. There was no clear
effect of multivitamin use. But I said
some key words there. Invasive cancer,
which is actually different from total
cancer. that matters because the
definition is narrower and assumes a
more progressive cancer. Now, I don't
mean housing reform. I mean it is not
precancerous or stage one cancer. That
matters because now we're measuring
something a bit more difficult to
detect. This means in short that studies
looking at total cancer risk tend to
indicate a benefit, but the effect on
more established cancers may not show.
In fact, a similar story is true when
looking at cancer related mortality.
There's generally no relationship
detected. And generally, the reason for
these differences in results comes down
to different study designs. I've cited a
few randomized control trials, but also
some associative studies. And keep in
mind that multivitamin formulations are
all over the place. So, the differences
between studies can be heavily impacted
by the type of multivitamin used or as I
mentioned, the outcome being assessed.
So cancer occurrence simply happens more
than cancer deaths. More people will get
cancer than people will die from cancer.
Which means that the amount of data that
can be collected to detect differences,
especially subtle differences, is far
greater for cancer occurrence. The point
being, there's a lot of reasons why
studies would disagree. And that leads
us to a huge difference between men and
women. You know all of what I just told
you about multivitamins being effective
against getting cancer, but maybe not
for preventing cancer death.
Chuck it. We've been discussing the data
in totality, men and women together. But
if you look at the data split by sex, a
completely different story emerges. For
example, if we reopen this study and I
show you the entirety of the data for
cancer incidents. Remember that's the
first one that we covered where multiple
studies indicate multivitamins were
effective. And we look at it with a
closer eye. We have total incidents up
top, men only in the middle and women
only at the bottom. The higher the
lines, more cancer. The intervention is
multivitamin.
Neither the total nor the women show any
effect of multivitamin use, but we see a
noticeable effect for men. In fact, in
that same study, the same was true for
mortality, too. That means that men
benefit from multivitamin consumption,
possibly even more than what we
previously went over, but women
experience a more muted benefit, if a
benefit at all. But the story doesn't
end there because there's another
concerning difference between the two
sexes. Before I dive into it, there's a
cancer specific data like lung,
prostate, breast, and others as well as
another factor that could impact
multivitamin usefulness. I'm covering
that in my full analysis of the one that
you're currently watching. It's included
as a small part of my Physionic Insider
membership, my premium research
platform. You also get a full article
and a one paragraph summary of the main
takeaways. And if you prefer everything
delivered to your email, there's an
exclusive email list for the insiders,
plus all these perks right over here.
And if you'd like to have full access to
all my work, consider joining the
insiders. The link to join is in the
description box. The reality is that
there are even signals of a specific
type of cancer that is actually worsened
in risk from multivitamin consumption.
That cancer is non-hodkkins lymphoma, a
type of immune cell cancer specific to
white blood cells. And if we look at
that data transformed by yours truly, we
see the relationship based on the length
of time of consuming vit multivitamins.
The more right the lines and dots go,
the greater the risk of a particular
type of lymphoma. And you can see that
at the very bottom condition, the
longest exposure to multivitamins
indicates greatest risk. While
associative, the researchers did measure
an account for many influencing factors.
Though the association that we just saw
was again only in women with no such
link in men. Yet the researchers failed
to control for menop menopausal status.
though they did control for age. It's
possible that menopausal status could
influence the relationship here
considering the drastic change in
hormonal profile. Plus, the researchers
themselves admit that this single
positive result with cancer could be due
to chance. Meaning that if you do enough
measurements, uh, one of them is bound
to show a statistically identified
difference, though there is no real
effect. Adding to that, a later analysis
by the same research group looked at the
same lymphoma but quantified death
instead of incidents like what we went
over earlier. And counterintuitively,
they detected no relationship between
women and non-hodkkins lymphoma related
death. I'm going to get into a little
research methodology to explain the
differences between these studies. So,
if you want to skip, just skip to this
timestamp. There's three primary
reasons. So one, the second study on
mortality used a weaker cohort or group
of people. I don't mean physically weak.
I mean the data collection wasn't as
robust because they only measured
multivitamin use at the beginning of the
study and the study lasted for 14 years.
One of the strengths of that data set
over the incident study is that it
showed a relationship with lymphoma is
that the group tested were more
heterogeneous or different because the
incident study while they did measure
multivitamin use multiple times
throughout it was restricted to nurses.
So the relationship may be specific to
nurses who consume multivitamins on a
regular basis and not necessarily other
women who consume multivitamins
regularly. The second reason is simply
duration of the study. So one study
lasted for 14 years and another lasted
for 16 years. Honestly, I doubt that
that makes a huge difference, but it
could play a factor. And third, when
we're returning to the mortality versus
incidents, one is going to simply
collect more data to detect a difference
than the other. I'm talking about
incidents. I could go on honestly, but
if you made the mistake of not jumping
ahead, you're probably already
regretting not fasttracking to the
answer. So, let's get to it. There isn't
any corroborative data to substantiate
or refute the study indicating a link
between multivitamin use and lymphoma.
So, we're in a bit of a bind here.
Still, I'll take my best stab at a
reasonable conclusion here. If you're a
man, multivitamin consumption
Acknowledging the flaws in the data like
not knowing the multivitamin use is
generally a neutral or positive health
investment on the cancer front. Multiv
multivitamins offer a small protective
effect. It's not massive, but it is
there. If you're a woman, multivitamin
consumption, acknowledging even more
uncertainty in the data, does indicate
some positives on the cancer front, but
most of it is quite neutral. If you have
a family history of non-hodkkins
lymphoma, then maybe consider reducing
the amount that you consume or avoid
them and simply stick to a well-
balanced diet. Otherwise, I don't see
much reason to avoid multivitamins,
especially since we're limiting it to
cancer here. And there may be other
benefits of multivitamins beyond the
scope of cancer. But let's say that
you're not convinced and you'd want even
more evidence on the potential benefits
of simple multivitamins. I cover some
compelling reasons right here.
I know this was a bit convoluted and
sometimes the data just pans out that
way, but I hope that this was
informative and I'll see you in the next
one. Bye.